Finding Aid for the Wilbur Fisk Tillett Papers
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
Wilbur Fisk Tillett Papers
multiple
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0457
2.1 linear_feet
A Chronology
Born: August 25, 1854 in Hendersonville, North Carolina, to John Tillett and Elizabeth Jenkins Wyche Tillett.
1871 Enrolled at Trinity College, now Duke University
1873 Transferred to Randolph-Macon
1876-77 Instructor in English and Mathematics at Randolph-Macon
1877 Entered Princeton Theological Seminary
1879 Master of Arts from Princeton
1880 Received into Virginia Conference of Methodist Episcopal Church, South and appointed pastor of Lynn Street Church, Danville, Virginia
1882 Began teaching career at Vanderbilt through influence of Bishop Holland N. McTyeire. First Chaplain of the university as well as teacher of Systematic Theology.
1883 Adjunct professor of Systematic Theology
1884 Full professor of Systematic Theology 1886-1919 Dean of the Biblical Dept. and Vice-chancellor
1888 Married Kate Schoolfield, who died in 1889.
1889 Member of committee compiling the Hymn Book of the Methodist Episcopal Church, South
1894 Married Laura Elizabeth McCloud
1899-1930 Member of Board of Education of Tennessee Conference of M.E. Church, South
1902 Published Personal Salvation: Studies in Christian Doctrine Pertaining to the Spiritual Life - one of his most widely read books
1905 Member of Commission preparing the Methodist Hymnal
1910-1914 Member of General Board of Education of M.E. Church, South
1912 Member of the Executive Committee of Federal Council of the Churches of Christ in America
1919-1936 Dean Emeritus of Vanderbilt Biblical Department
1936 Died
Source: Lester H. Colloms. Wilbur Fisk Tillett. Louisville The Cloister Press, 1949.
Diplomas and Certificates:
W. F. Tillett
Doctor of Sacred Theology - Northwestern University.
Doctor of Sacred Theology - Wesleyan University.
Laura E. McCloud
Mistress of Arts and Science - Ashville Female College
Kate S. Tillett (daughter)
Certificate of Proficiency - Ward Seminary for Young Ladies.
Special Certificate - Ward Seminary for Young Ladies.
B. A.-Randolph-Macon College
M. A. - Vanderbilt University
M. A. - University of Wisconsin
Pi Gamma Mu Membership
- Correspondence - Outgoing - Consisting of 24 letters, mostly carbon copies. Arranged chronologically. Two letters are undated and are placed at the end., Consisting of 24 letters, mostly carbon copies. Arranged chronologically. Two letters are undated and are placed at the end. (Box 1, Folder 1-5)
- Correspondence - Incoming, Total of 84 letters. Three postcards. Majority in typescript. (Box 1, Folder 6-16)
- Printed New Year Greeting Cards signed by Dr. Tillett (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Pocket Calendars (5), 1898, 1900, 1901, 1902, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Pocket-size notebook containing sermon material (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Personal notes on various subjects - holograph (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Notes relating to hymn studies and book on annotated hymns. MSS of chapters (Box 1, Folder 21-24)
- Ms Material for Published Work on Hymns (Box 1, Folder 25-32)
- Ms Material for Published Work on Hymns (Box 2, Folder 25-32)
- Poems. 13 pieces. Arranged alphabetically by title (Box 2, Folder 33)
- Songs - Two songs for which Dr. Tillett wrote the words. “My Father Knows” - 2 copies; “O Vanderbilt: Dear Vanderbilt!” - 3 copies (Box 2, Folder 34)
- Publication by Dr. Tillett - 25 pamphlets; 1 book (Box 2, Folder 35-39)
- Bibles. Two New Testaments (Box 2, Folder 40)
- The Methodist Hymnal - leather bound (Box 2, Folder 41)
- Reviews of Dr. Tillett’s Books. “A Book That Will Live”; “Hymns and Hymn Writers of the Church”; “A Statement of the Faith of World-Wide Methodism - 2 copies (Box 3, Folder 42)
- Business Papers (Box 3, Folder 42)
- Tillett’s Obituary - Ms. (Box 3, Folder 43)
- Publications and Articles by Other Authors. 7 pamphlets; 2 typescript articles. Arranged alphabetically by title (Box 3, Folder 44-45)
- Miscellaneous. 14 items. Including Vanderbilt Commencement program, 2 pamphlets, one photograph, announcements, one typed anecdote, one copy of partial charter of Emory University, etc. (Box 3, Folder 46)
- Newspaper and Magazine Clippings - Alphabetically arranged according to subject (Box 3, Folder 47-67)
- Small Scrapbook of Dr. Tillett. Large Scrapbook placed separately with Ms boxes (Box 4, Folder 68)
- Volume of Letters of Appreciation on Occasion of Dr. Tillett’s Retirement (Box 4, Folder 69)
- Galliard’s Hymn of Adam and Eve, out of Fifth Book of Milton’s Paradise Lost (1728) (Box 4, Folder 70)
- Nine Diplomas and Certificates placed separately in red tubed container next to Ms boxes (Box 4)
- List of Incoming Correspondents
  - Atkinson, J. C, April 30, 1914; 1
  - Bartlett, S, July 20, 1911. postcard; 1
  - Bastick, J. A, April 16, 1914; 1
  - Beeue, Dow B, Sept. 3, 1910; 1
  - Bingham, J. R, postmarked April 21, 1914. postcard; 1
  - Blackwell, R. E, April 21, 1914; 1
  - Brooks, Cleanth, April 17, 1914; 1
  - Chao, T. C, Sept. 16, 1926; 1
  - Cram, w. G., et. al, Aug. 2, 1928; 1
  - Creel, E. K, April 18, 1914; 1
  - Crowe, H. P, April 18, 1914; 1
  - Curry, J. T, April 24, 1914; 1
  - Day, F. L, April 23, 1914; 1
  - Duke, B. N, Sept. 11, 1926; 1
  - Dumville, Samuel L, n.d; 1
  - Elliott, George, March 6, 1925; 1
  - Evans, M. O, Nov. 2, 1910; 1
  - Fisher, Sterling, April 20, 1914; 1
  - Fitzhugh, G. T. and Biggs, Albert W, Feb. 12, 1913; 1
  - Foster, R. N, Dec. 21, 1903; 1
  - Game, Jonah? B, April 18, 1914; 1
  - Garrison, W. E, April 9, 1927; 1
  - Green, S. D, Jan. 29, 1925; Feb. 23, 1925; 2
  - Grogan, Jas. D, April 18, 1914; 1
  - Hamill, H. M, May 25, 1912; June 9, 1912; April 22, 1914; 3
  - Hoss, E. E, Feb. 27, 1912; 1
  - Howard, A. T, Nov. 3, 1926; 1
  - Hughes, Edwin H, June 1, 1927; 1
  - Kern, Paul B, April 17, 1914; 1
  - Key, D. M, April 6, 1927; 1
  - Kimmel, G. B, Nov. 22, 1926; 1
  - Kirkland, J. H, April 26, 1935; March 25, 1935; Jan. 6, 1936; Feb. 4, 1936 - enclosure. Feb 24, 1936; June 18, 1936 - enclosure; 6
  - Lanneau, A. W, April 21, 1903; 1
  - Lanius, Carol V, April 25, 1914; 1
  - Lee, James W, ? 1914; 1
  - McClain, R. P, April 21, 1914; 1
  - McConnell, March 27, 1923; 1
  - Miley, Jno, Nov. 16, 1886; 1
  - Moose, William L, April 21, 1914; 1
  - Morgan, J. B, June 15, 1909 to Maj. F. P. McWhirter; 1
  - Mullins, E. G, Aug. 30, 1910; 1
  - Mullowney, John J, Aug. 20, 1926; 1
  - Nuelson, John L, Jan. 6, 1910; Feb. 14, 1910; March 17, 1910 March 24, 1910; Aug. 3, 1910; 5
  - Nutter, C. S, Jan. 2, 1912; 1
  - Page, Walter H, Jan. 3, 1918; 1
  - Paine, Silas H, Dec. 14, 1891; 1
  - Perry, Mrs. J. W, June 15, 1931; 1
  - Pettyjohn, John P. & Co., April 20, 1914; 1
  - Pollitt, F. S, April 22, 1914; 1
  - Pope, R. B, March 31, 1895; 1
  - Powell, Nathan, April 18, 1914; 1
  - Price, Carl F, May 29, 1911; July 11, 1911; 2
  - Rockefeller, John D., Jr, Nov. 24, 1926; 1
  - Romine, W. B, April 26, 1914; 1
  - Scales, James R, July 16, 1912; 1
  - Seay, Frank, April 24, 1914; 1
  - Sessions, T. F, April 19, 1914; 1
  - Sipple, B. D, April 25, 1914; 1
  - Smith, A. Frank, June 5, 1930; 1
  - Stamey, E. L, April 20, 1914; 1
  - Stevens, George Barker, May 1, 1902; 1
  - Stoves, George, Oct. 27, 1933; 1
  - Telford, John, May 1, 1911; Feb. 21, 1912; 2
  - Tillett, Charles, Aug. 30, 1926; 1
  - Tillett, H. A. (Gus), Oct. 23, 1928; 1
  - Tucker, J. Woffard, June 18, 1889; 1
  - Wasson, S. E, April 17, 1914; 1
  - Weaver, Lester, April 16, 1914; 1
  - Webb, W. R, April 23, 1927; 1
  - White, Allene, April 23, 1927; 1
  - Whiteside, Warren T, April 18, 1914; 1
  - Young, Jesse Bowman, April 18, 1914; 1
- Titles of Poems
  - “A Faith That Cannot Know Defeat”, 2 copies
  - “The Best is Yet to Be”, (also editorial included on p. 37 of paper)
  - “But Her Heart Can See”, 2 copies
  - “For Friends Like You”
  - “The Incarnation”
  - “O Vanderbilt! Dear Vanderbilt!”
  - “Some Things God Might Have Done But Didn’t, 2 copies
  - “A Sermon in Song”, 3 copies
  - “A Vane Sermon”
  - “We Do Out Part”
  - “Heaven Holiest Song of Love”
- Titles of Publications
  - A Call to Preach, 2 copies
  - The Conditions of Church Membership
  - Creed and Character, 3 copies
  - The Date and Authorship of the Book of Daniel, 2 copies
  - The Future of the Biblical Department of Vanderbilt University
  - The Hand of God in American History, 2 copies
  - The Passion for Righteousness
  - The Rights and Duties of the Methodist Episcopal Church, South in Vanderbilt University
  - Seed Corn for the World
  - The South’s Greatest Teacher of Boys, 2 copies
  - A Statement of the Faith of World-Wide Methodism, 3 copies
  - Theological Seminaries and Teacher Training
  - Vanderbilt Biblical Institute
- Pamphlets and Articles by Other Authors
  - Biographical Index of the Authors of the Hymns - no author given
  - Essentials of Vocational Information, 2 copies; Kate S. Tillett
  - Hymn Festival Programs, Carl F. Price
  - “Jesus the World Soul”, V. M. Collins
  - Old ‘Sawney’, Ida Clyde Clarke
  - The Praise of the Virgin in Early Latin Hymns, Ruth Ellis Messenger
  - The Religious Value of Hymns, William P. Merrill
  - The Significance of the Old French Psalter, Waldo Selden Pratt; Last three pamphlets and Hymn Festival Programs are part of a series edited by Carl F. Price, The Papers of the Hymn Society.
- Categories of Clippings
  - Andrew Jackson
  - Articles by Tillett
  - Articles About Tillet
  - Book Reviews of Tillett’s Books
  - Book Reviews Of Other Books
  - Drinking and Prohibition
  - Education
  - History
  - The Methodist Church
  - Missions
  - Music
  - Obituaries
  - Religious Doctrines
  - Doctrine of Sanctification
  - Sunday Observance
  - Vanderbilt
  - Miscellaneous
List of Correspondents in Volume of Letters of Appreciation
Abney, O. M.
Ader, O. P.
Akin, J. G.
Alexander, Will W.
Ashida, Keiji
Baker, W. L.
Baker, Ward McKim
Beale, George L.
Beauchamp, W. B.
Bourne, William R.
Bowen, C. A.
Briuson, Summers
Brooks, Joseph H.
Browne, O. E.
Buyers, Paul E.
Campbell, C. K.
Campbell, H. U.
Campbell, Will B.
Candler, B. T.
Canter, H. M.
Carre, Henry Beach
Carter, Cullen T.
Chambers, Herbert O.
Chao, T. C.
Christian, W. Asbury
Clark, Blmer T.
Clement, A. E.
Cook, Edmund F.
Cook, Osgood F.
Cooper, G. F.
Cooper, Oscar T.
C-?, Theodore
Corder, W. B.
Cowan, H.
Grady Craig, R. J.
Crowe, C. R.
Crowe, Fletcher S.
Cuninggins, J.
Curtis, W. M.
Davis, W. A.
Day, Frank C. L.
Demaree, T. W. B.
Dempsey, Elam F.
Dixon, J. W.
Dowd, O. W.
Duncan, Berry Jackson
Dunkle, William F.
Ellison, R. R.
Evans, George J.
Flinn, Glenn
Gamble, Foster K.
Givens, Claude P.
Glasgow, B. B.
Glass, H. I.
Greene, C. J.
Gunter, A. L.
H-?, Thos.
Hagler, J. A.
Hall, W. B.
Hargis, Geo. E.
Hawlains, R. M.
Hornbach, J. M.
Hounshell, C. G.
Hutchinson, Forney
Irion, J. W.
Joyner, N. E.
Kern, Paul B.
King W. P.
Klyer, W. H.
Kubota, G.
Lanius, Carol V.
Lewis, E. D.
Lewis, J. D.
Li, Tien Chuch
Long, Lem R.
Lowe, L. D.
Lowrey, P. O.
Luton, J. P.
Matsumoto, M.
May, John Albert
Menard, W. T.
Moore, E. G.
Moore, Leland
Moore, Roy
Morgan, George A.
Morgan, J. J.
Muraoka, Buichi
Murata, T.
McCullock, J. E.
Mcculloch, J. E.
McGeehee, Chas. D.
McLeod, N. B.
Nakamura, Kinzi
Naylor, George D.
Nelson, Jno. R.
Nelson, J. W.
Odell, Edson K.
Ormond, J. M.
Owens, H. Bascowe
Oxford, J. S.
Parsons, J.
Robert Pennington, B. B.
Perry, Louis C.
Phaup, LeRoy J.
Pipkin, Charles W.
Powell, Paul S.
Purcell, Clare
Ragsdale, T. C.
Ratledge, A. P.
Rawlings, E. H.
Rector, G. C.
Reves, Claude M.
Ricks, Wm. B.
Ruff, Robert H.
Ruyle, C. E.
Ryang, J. S.
Seay, Frank
Senchker, James Seehorn
Simpson, Claude M.
Shackford, John W.
Slaton, S. T.
Smith, G. F.
Smith, Wesley M.
Stevenson, Henry M.
Stevenson, R. E.
Stodghill, T. Whitt
Stokes, Henry
Stowe, J. J.
Tally, Charles T.
Tanaka, Y.
Taylor, J. F.
Touchstone, C.
Towson, Willard E.
Turrentine, S. B.
Tylen, Frank A.
Waiter, Bennett T.
Ware, W. R.
Waterfield, Clough A.
Weaver, Lester
Welburn, William D.
Wells, Frank L.
Wiggins, C. E.
Willcoxon, J. T.
Wilson, M. E.
Wilson, N. H. D.
Wynn, R. H.